<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BMC Syst Biol</journal-id><journal-title>BMC Systems Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="epub">1752-0509</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18793442</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2569920</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1752-0509-2-79</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-2-79</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction of <italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>KT2440: <italic>i</italic>JN746 as a cell factory</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="A1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>Juan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><email>jnogales@cib.csic.es</email></contrib><contrib id="A2" corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>Bernhard &#x000d8;</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>bpalsson@bioeng.ucsd.edu</email></contrib><contrib id="A3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>Ines</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>ithiele@ucsd.edu</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Departamento de Microbiolog&#x000ed;a Molecular, Centro de Investigaciones Biol&#x000f3;gicas-CSIC, Ramiro de Maeztu 9, Madrid, 28040, Spain</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Department of Bioengineering, University of California, San Diego, Gilman Drive 9500, 92093 La Jolla, CA, USA</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>PhD program in Bioinformatics, University of California, San Diego, Gilman Drive 9500, 92093 La Jolla, CA, USA</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2008</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biomedcentral.com/1752-0509/2/79"/><history><date date-type="received"><day>5</day><month>3</month><year>2008</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>9</month><year>2008</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2008 Nogales et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2008</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Nogales et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</p><!--<rdf xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms"><Work xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" rdf:about=""><license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"/><dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text"/><dc:author>
               Nogales
               Juan
               
               jnogales@cib.csic.es
            </dc:author><dc:title>
            A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction of Pseudomonas putida KT2440: iJN746 as a cell factory
         </dc:title><dc:date>2008</dc:date><dcterms:bibliographicCitation>BMC Systems Biology 2(1): 79-. (2008)</dcterms:bibliographicCitation><dc:identifier type="sici">1752-0509(2008)2:1&#x0003c;79&#x0003e;</dc:identifier><dcterms:isPartOf>urn:ISSN:1752-0509</dcterms:isPartOf><License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" xmlns=""/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" xmlns=""/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" xmlns=""/></License></Work></rdf>--></license></permissions><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>is the best studied pollutant degradative bacteria and is harnessed by industrial biotechnology to synthesize fine chemicals. Since the publication of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440's genome, some <italic>in silico </italic>analyses of its metabolic and biotechnology capacities have been published. However, global understanding of the capabilities of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 requires the construction of a metabolic model that enables the integration of classical experimental data along with genomic and high-throughput data. The constraint-based reconstruction and analysis (COBRA) approach has been successfully used to build and analyze <italic>in silico </italic>genome-scale metabolic reconstructions.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>We present a genome-scale reconstruction of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440's metabolism, <italic>i</italic>JN746, which was constructed based on genomic, biochemical, and physiological information. This manually-curated reconstruction accounts for 746 genes, 950 reactions, and 911 metabolites. <italic>i</italic>JN746 captures biotechnologically relevant pathways, including polyhydroxyalkanoate synthesis and catabolic pathways of aromatic compounds (e.g., toluene, benzoate, phenylacetate, nicotinate), not described in other metabolic reconstructions or biochemical databases. The predictive potential of <italic>i</italic>JN746 was validated using experimental data including growth performance and gene deletion studies. Furthermore, <italic>in silico </italic>growth on toluene was found to be oxygen-limited, suggesting the existence of oxygen-efficient pathways not yet annotated in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s genome. Moreover, we evaluated the production efficiency of polyhydroxyalkanoates from various carbon sources and found fatty acids as the most prominent candidates, as expected.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Here we presented the first genome-scale reconstruction of <italic>P. putida</italic>, a biotechnologically interesting all-surrounder. Taken together, this work illustrates the utility of <italic>i</italic>JN746 as i) a knowledge-base, ii) a discovery tool, and iii) an engineering platform to explore <italic>P. putida</italic>'s potential in bioremediation and bioplastic production.</p></sec></abstract></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p><italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>is a non-pathogenic member of rRNA group I of the genus <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>that colonizes many different environments and is well known for its broad metabolic versatility and genetic plasticity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 is a TOL plasmid cured, spontaneous restriction deficient derivative of <italic>P. putida </italic>mt-2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. This strain represents the first host-vector biosafety system for cloning in gram-negative soil bacteria and hence, has been extensively used as a host for gene cloning and expression of heterologous genes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. Consequently, large efforts have been made in exploiting these capacities in a diverse range of biotechnological applications including i) bioremediation of contaminated areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]; ii) quality improvement of fossil fuels, e.g., by desulphurization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]; iii) biocatalytic production of fine chemicals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>]; iv) production of bioplastic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]; and v) as agents of plant growth promotion and plant pest control [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p><p>Since the publication of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440's genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], our knowledge about this strain has significantly increased [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and various "-omics" data sets have become available, such as transcriptomic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>], proteomic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], and fluxomic data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Subsequently, some <italic>in silico </italic>analyses of its metabolic and biotechnological capacities have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. However, systemic understanding of metabolic and biotechnology capabilities of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 requires the construction of a more comprehensive model enabling the integration of the canonical experimental data along with genomic and high-throughput data in a hierarchical and coherent fashion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>].</p><p>The constraint-based reconstruction and analysis (COBRA) approach is one possible modeling approach that uses stoichiometric information about biochemical transformation taking place in a target organism to construct the model. While a metabolic reconstruction is unique to the target organism one can derive many different condition-specific models from a single reconstruction. This conversion of a metabolic reconstruction of an organism into models requires the imposition of physicochemical and environmental constraints to define systems boundaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. The conversion also includes the transformation of the reaction list into a computable, mathematical matrix format. In this so-called S matrix, where S stands for stoichiometric, the rows correspond to the network metabolites and the columns to the network reactions. The coefficients of the substrates and products of each reaction are entered in the corresponding cell of the matrix. This conversion can be done automatically (e.g., using the Matlab-based COBRA toolbox [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]). Once in this format, numerous mathematical tools can be used to interrogate the metabolic network properties <italic>in silico</italic>. Many of the published mathematical tools have been reviewed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and encoded in Matlab format [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. A large subset of these tools relies on linear programming (LP), a mathematical tool used to find a solution to an optimization problem (e.g., maximal possible growth rate of my metabolic network under a given set of environmental constraints). While LP-based tools are very helpful in studying reconstructed metabolic networks, some questions may better be addressed without having to choose an objective function. Those methods are called unbiased methods, in contrast to biased LP-based methods, because they identify all feasible flux distributions under the given set of environmental constraints rather than only the optimal distributions. The COBRA approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] has been successfully used to build and analyze genome-scale <italic>in silico </italic>reconstructions for representatives of archaea (e.g.,<italic>Methanosarcina barkeri </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]), of bacteria (e.g., <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]; <italic>B. subtilis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]; <italic>H. pylori </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]; <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]; <italic>S. aureus </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]; <italic>L. lactis </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]), and of eukarya (e.g., Human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]). The numerous mathematical tools have been used for i) identification and filling of knowledge gaps (e.g. missing gene annotations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]); ii) prediction of the outcome of adaptive evolution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>]; iii) design of engineered production strains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>]; and iv) the understanding of topological features of metabolic networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. A recent review illustrates the variety of questions that have been addressed to <italic>E. coli</italic>'s metabolic network using different biased and unbiased COBRA methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>].</p><p>Here, we describe a highly detailed, genome-scale, metabolic reconstruction of <italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>KT2440. Based on the naming convention for metabolic networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>], this genome scale reconstruction was deemed <italic>i</italic>JN746, where <italic><underline>i</underline></italic> stands for <italic>in silico</italic>, JN are the initials of the constructor, and 746 corresponds to the number of included metabolic genes. The reconstruction was built using the COBRA approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] and validated using flux balance analysis (FBA, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]). The <italic>in silico </italic>metabolic network was further evaluated by comparing i) predicted growth rate capacities in different carbon sources and ii) predicted essential genes with experimental data from <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. Finally, we show the utility of the <italic>P. putida </italic>reconstruction to analyze its biodegradative (i.e. toluene degradation) and biotechnological (i.e. bioplastic production) capacities.</p></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><sec><title>Characteristics of the metabolic reconstruction of <italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>KT2440</title><p>The metabolic reconstruction of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440, <italic>i</italic>JN746, was constructed based on its annotated genome sequence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>], primary and review publications, various genetic and biochemical databases (i.e., KEGG Database [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], PSEUDOCYC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], and SYSTOMONAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]), and biochemical information found in <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>-specific [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] and biochemical textbooks.</p><p><italic>i</italic>JN746 accounts for 746 open reading frames (ORF), whose corresponding gene products are involved in 810 metabolic and transport reactions (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). A total of 140 non-gene associated reactions were included in <italic>i</italic>JN746 based on physiological evidence in literature supporting their presence in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolism. Hence, the reconstruction captures a total of 950 metabolic reactions and 911 metabolites distributed over three different cellular compartments: cytoplasm, periplasm, and extracellular space. Each metabolite was placed in one or more of these compartments depending on the cellular localization of the catalyzing enzyme, and the flux across outer and inner membranes was enabled by transport reactions.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Properties of metabolic reconstruction of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold><italic>Reconstruction &#x00026; Organism</italic></bold><break/><bold></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>iJN746 </italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>P. putida</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>iAF1260 </italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>E. coli</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>iYO844 </italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>B. subtilis</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>iNJ661 </italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>M. tuberculosis</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>iMO1056 </italic></bold><break/><bold><italic>P. aeruginosa</italic></bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Protein coding genes per genome</td><td align="center">5,350<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">4,464<sup>b</sup></td><td align="center">4,106<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">3,989<sup>a</sup></td><td align="center">5669</td></tr><tr><td align="center">SKI value<sup>c</sup></td><td align="center">0.74</td><td align="center">55.87</td><td align="center">4.97</td><td align="center">7.84</td><td align="center">5.12</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Genes (% of genome)</td><td align="center">746 (14%)</td><td align="center">1260 (28%)</td><td align="center">844 (21%)</td><td align="center">661 (17%)</td><td align="center">1056 (18,6%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Reactions</td><td align="center">950</td><td align="center">2077</td><td align="center">1020</td><td align="center">939</td><td align="center">883</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Gene-reaction associated</td><td align="center">810</td><td align="center">1919</td><td align="center">904</td><td align="center">723</td><td align="center">839</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Non-gene- associated network reaction (% of network reactions)</td><td align="center">140 (17%)</td><td align="center">158 (8%)</td><td align="center">116 (13%)</td><td align="center">116 (16%)</td><td align="center">44 (5%)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Exchange reactions</td><td align="center">90</td><td align="center">304</td><td align="center">225</td><td align="center">88</td><td align="center">-</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Metabolites</td><td align="center">911</td><td align="center">1039</td><td align="center">988</td><td align="center">828</td><td align="center">-</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Properties of metabolic reconstruction of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 were compared with recently published metabolic reconstructions of <italic>E. coli </italic>MG1655 (<italic>i</italic>AF1260 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]), <italic>B. subtilis </italic>(<italic>i</italic>YO844 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]), and <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv (<italic>i</italic>NJ661 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]) and <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic> (iMO1056 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]). <sup>a </sup>taken from KEGG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>]; <sup>b </sup>based on Riley et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>]; <sup>c </sup>Species Knowledge Index (SKI) was calculated as described in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>The reactions included in <italic>i</italic>JN746 were divided into 55 specific pathways, or subsystems, based on their functional role (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1A</xref>). In general, the transport subsystem was found to be the subsystem with the highest number of gene-associated reactions, highlighting the importance of cellular transport for <italic>P. putida</italic>. This observation agrees well with the known lifestyle of <italic>P. putida </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] and successfully reflects the fact that approx. 12% of <italic>P. putida </italic>genome encodes for transport-associated gene products [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Reactions related to amino acid metabolism were also found to be very important since the de novo synthesis pathways for all 20 amino acids are present in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s genome [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>]. Moreover, <italic>P. putida </italic>is known for its capability to utilize many amino acids as a carbon and nitrogen source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>]. A third group of great importance contained reactions involved in aromatic acid degradation pathways, which reflects the physiological ability of <italic>P. putida </italic>to use many of these compounds as a carbon and energy source (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Furthermore, despite the absence of the TOL pathway in KT2440's genome, the plasmid genes and the corresponding reactions were included into the <italic>P. putida </italic>metabolic reconstruction since the TOL plasmid is present in the parental strain <italic>P. putida </italic>mt-2 and this paradigmatic plasmid is often used to expand <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440's metabolic capacities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Finally, reactions associated with lipid metabolism constituted another important subsystem group. In fact, <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 can synthesize and accumulate <underline>m</underline>edium-<underline>s</underline>ide-<underline>c</underline>hain <underline>p</underline>oly<underline>h</underline>ydroxy<underline>a</underline>lkanoate<underline>s</underline> (msc-PHAs), which are lipid related polymers, from a wide range of carbon sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. This ability is of special interest for biotechnological purposes (reviewed in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]) and therefore, we incorporated both the msc-PHAs biosynthetic and TOL biodegradative pathways into the metabolic reconstruction (see below).</p><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>A</bold>. <bold>Pie chart showing the distribution of <italic>i</italic>JN746's intracellular reactions over the different subsystems.</bold> The number of reactions per subsystem is shown and subsystems of high importance were highlighted in bold. <bold>B</bold>. Heat map of the confidence score of the different subsystems in <italic>i</italic>JN746. The 4 rows in the map represent the different confidence score (from left to right: 4, 3, 2, 1). The various colors correspond to the percentage of subsystems reactions that have the corresponding confidence score (red = 100%, blue = 0%). The confidence level was based on a scale from 1 to 4. A level, or score, of 4 corresponds to biochemical evidence for a gene product and its reaction(s); 3 represents physiological, genetic, or proteomic evidence; 2 corresponds to only sequence-based evidence for a gene product and its reaction(s); and finally a score of 1 reflects that the reaction had to be included for model functionality (e. g., production of biomass precursor).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>General depiction of the aromatic compound degradation routes present in <italic>i</italic>JN746.</bold> The protocatechuate (pca genes) and catechol (cat genes) branches of the beta-ketoadipate pathway are shown as well as peripheral pathways by orange arrows. The homogentisate pathway (hmg genes) is represented by green arrows and the phenylacetate pathway (paa genes) is represented by purple arrows. The nicotinate and gallate pathways (unknown genes) are shown by green and red arrows, respectively. Finally, the Tol pathway (xyl genes from pWW0 plasmid) for toluene and xylene degradation is represented by blue arrows. The initial aromatic compounds are indicated by green circles and the central metabolic compounds for each pathway are also highlighted. A detailed list of reactions involved in aromatic acid degradation can be found in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-2"/></fig><p>Every network reaction was associated with confidence scores based on the available evidence for its presence in the <italic>P. putida </italic>metabolic network (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). For instance, reactions whose enzymes have been biochemically studied in <italic>P. putida </italic>received a confidence score of 4. If physiological or genetic knockout information was available, a score of 3 was associated with the network reaction. Reactions associated with enzymes that were only annotated in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s genome but had no further experimental evidence were given a confidence score of 2. Finally, during the evaluation of the network functionality (i.e. biomass precursor production) some reactions had to be added to the network for which no genetic or experimental evidence could be found. Those reactions represent modeling hypotheses, which need further experimental validation and thus received a confidence score of 1. Upon completion, the reconstruction had an overall average confidence score of 2.83. In fact, two thirds of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolic pathways have been very well or well studied, while only a third of the subsystems were primarily based on the genome annotation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1B</xref>). This high level of confidence is also reflected by the number of references that lead to this metabolic reconstruction. Almost 90% of the internal reactions (844) have at least one associated citation, while a total of 176 unique primary and review publications were reviewed and incorporated into this reconstruction. Subsequently, this first genome-scale reconstruction of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolism represents a comprehensive knowledge base summarizing and categorizing the information currently available. The content of this knowledge base will be easily accessible through the BiGG database <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://BiGG.ucsd.edu"/>.</p></sec><sec><title>Comparison of scope and content of <italic>i</italic>JN746 with published metabolic networks</title><p>The properties of <italic>i</italic>JN746 were compared with the properties of recently published reconstructions of <italic>E. coli </italic>MG1655 (<italic>i</italic>AF1260, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]), <italic>B. subtilis </italic>(<italic>i</italic>YO844 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]), <italic>M. tuberculosis </italic>H37Rv (<italic>i</italic>NJ661 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]), and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>PAO1 (<italic>i</italic>MO1056 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>] (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). We found that the percentage of included ORFs was smaller in <italic>i</italic>JN746 than in the other reconstructions. Subsequently, it can be expected that the number of metabolic functions present in <italic>P. putida </italic>is larger than currently identified in the genome annotation and literature. In fact, the number of included non-gene associated reactions was twice that of the <italic>E. coli </italic>metabolic reconstruction. Furthermore, the species knowledge index (SKI) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>], which relates the number of PubMed abstracts of an organism to its number of ORFs, was much lower for <italic>P. putida </italic>compared to the other reconstructions. In summary, this comparison indicates that the overall context coverage in <italic>i</italic>JN746 is comparable with other high-quality network reconstructions when the amount of available literature is considered.</p><p>A metabolic reconstruction for another representative of the <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>genera was published recently [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. A comparison of <italic>P. putida </italic>and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>metabolic reconstructions was performed (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). In contrast to <italic>P. putida</italic>, <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>is an opportunistic human pathogen and as such more information about its metabolism and physiology is available, which is directly reflected by a SKI value 7 times higher than that of <italic>P. putida </italic>(Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>). As a consequence, a larger number of metabolic genes were included in the metabolic reconstruction (14% of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s genome vs. 18% of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>'s genome). Despite being close relatives, these two representatives have significant differences in lifestyle and metabolic capabilities. Subsequently, the two metabolic reconstructions have significant differences, emphasizing the importance of organism-specific reconstructions. For instance, the <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>reconstruction contains pathways necessary for growth and production of common virulence factors, including alginate, rhamnolipids, phenezines, and quorum-sensing molecules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>], which are not present in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolic network. In contrast, <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>'s metabolic network does not account for pathways necessary to degrade aromatic compounds.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>i</italic>JN746's metabolic versatility</title><p>Flux balance analysis (FBA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]) can provide insight into the growth capabilities of the reconstructed network. Comparison of <italic>in silico </italic>growth performance with experimental data allows for the assessment of the predictive potential of the metabolic reconstruction and thus represents a valuable tool for network evaluation. Furthermore, <italic>in silico </italic>growth analysis may expand the known array of carbon-, nitrogen-, and energy sources of the reconstructed organism. In this study, the aerobic growth capabilities of <italic>i</italic>JN746 in <italic>i</italic>M9 medium substituted with different carbon sources were determined qualitatively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) and quantitatively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The growth simulation results reflected the metabolic versatility for which <italic>P. putida </italic>is well known, with a total of 59 carbon sources enabling <italic>in silico </italic>growth when added to the <italic>i</italic>M9 minimal medium (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Furthermore, we compared the <italic>in silico </italic>growth performance on different carbon, sulfur, and nitrogen sources with phenotyping data derived from literature [see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>]. For instance, <italic>P. putida </italic>is found in terrestrial and aquatic environments around the world, with preference for the rhizosphere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], which is especially rich in carbon sources, amino acids, organic acids, and aromatic acids derived from seeds, roots, and other plant parts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>]. This niche specificity accounts for the broad carbon source usage of KT2440 and therefore, most of the known soil carbon sources were captured in <italic>i</italic>JN746 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Of particular biotechnological importance is the ability of <italic>i</italic>JN746 to metabolize aromatic compounds, thus, representing the first metabolic reconstruction accounting for growth on these carbon sources. For example, aromatic compounds such as toluene or xylene are of special interest as they are archetypical pollutants. Subsequently, we studied the toluene degradation process using <italic>i</italic>JN746 (see below).</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Carbon sources enabling growth of <italic>i</italic>JN746 in <italic>i</italic>M9 mineral medium.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold><italic>Class</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>Compound</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>Class</italic></bold></td><td align="center"><bold><italic>Compound</italic></bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Aromatic and related compounds</td><td></td><td align="center">Amino acids</td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Protocatechuate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Arginine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Caffeate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Aspartate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Oxoadipate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Glutamate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">4-Hydroxybenzoate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Glycine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Benzoate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Histidine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Catechol</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Isoleucine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Coniferyl alcohol</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Leucine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Ferulate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Lysine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Gallate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Proline</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">m-Xylene</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Serine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Nicotinate</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Threonine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">p-Xylene</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Valine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Phenylacetate</td><td align="center">Organics acids</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">L-Phenylalanine</td><td></td><td align="center">&#x003b1;-Ketoglutarate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Quinate</td><td></td><td align="center">Citrate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">p-Coumarate</td><td></td><td align="center">Fumarate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Toluene</td><td></td><td align="center">Isocitrate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">L-Tyrosine</td><td></td><td align="center">D-Lactate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Vanillin</td><td></td><td align="center">L-Lactate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Vanillate</td><td></td><td align="center">Malate</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Fatty acids</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Succinate</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Acetate</td><td align="center">Carbohydrates</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Decanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">2-ketogluconate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Dodecanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">D-Fructose</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Hexadecanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">D-Glucose</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Hexanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">D-Gluconate</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Octanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">D-Ribose</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Propionate</td><td align="center">Miscellaneous compounds</td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td></td><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Tetradecanoate</td><td></td><td align="center">4-Aminobuturate</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Polyalcohols and glycols</td><td></td><td></td><td align="center">Glycine betaine</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Glyceraldehyde</td><td></td><td align="center">Ornithine</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Glycerol</td><td></td><td align="center">Choline</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">Glycolate</td><td></td><td align="center">Choline sulfate</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Carbon sources enabling growth of <italic>i</italic>JN746 in <italic>i</italic>M9 mineral medium. The compounds were grouped based their structural characteristics. A complete list of carbon sources tested, along with possible nitrogen and sulfur sources, as well as bibliographic support can be found in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>No false positive carbon, nitrogen, or sulfur sources were found in <italic>i</italic>JN746, as expected, as only exchange reactions were included in the reconstruction for metabolites, which have been reported to be taken up or secreted by <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440. In contrast, some disagreements, such as false negatives, were observed despite a good overall agreement with the <italic>in vivo </italic>data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>]. For example, it was reported that <italic>P. putida </italic>can use L-alanine as a carbon- and nitrogen-source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>] but <italic>i</italic>JN746 cannot use this compound as a carbon or nitrogen source. This disagreement could not be resolved. In contrast, <italic>i</italic>JN746 was initially unable to use choline-O-sulphate, choline, or glycine betaine as carbon- and nitrogen-sources despite experimental evidence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. However, the addition of two non-gene-associated reactions, betaine-homocysteine S-methyltransferase (EC- 2.1.1.5) and dimethylglycine dehydrogenase (EC- 1.5.99.2), enabled <italic>i</italic>JN746 to use these metabolites as carbon- and nitrogen-sources through the glycine metabolism. In addition, choline-O-sulphate could also be used as sulfur source [see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>]. The two added reactions represent a hypothesis that needs further experimental verification. These examples show how discrepancies between <italic>in silico </italic>predictions and physiological properties can be used to drive new discoveries, as was shown for <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Growth on glucose</title><p><italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440, like other <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>species and rhizosymbionts, has an incomplete glycolytic pathway because of a missing 6-phosphofructokinase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. However, <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 has a complete Entner-Doudoroff pathway, which allows for the utilization of glucose and other sugars as carbon sources (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). Therefore, we investigated the properties of glucose metabolism in <italic>i</italic>JN746 to validate and evaluate the reconstructed network [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. For instance, comparison of predicted <italic>in silico </italic>growth with experimental data permits a direct assessment of the predictive potential of a reconstructed metabolic network. Subsequently, we determined the aerobic growth capability of <italic>i</italic>JN746 in Glucose-M9 minimal medium (<italic>i</italic>M9). Interestingly, <italic>i</italic>JN746 grew faster in glucose than experimental <italic>in vivo </italic>data suggested for <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2442 (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]). A similar difference in growth rate between <italic>in vivo </italic>and <italic>in silico </italic>measurements was reported for <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. The difference in growth rate might be explained by an incomplete formulation of biomass function or higher energy maintenance requirements not accounted for in the current reconstruction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] or missing adaptation to glucose as primary carbon source. Another explanation could be that <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2442 converts only a part of glucose into biomass. In fact, a recent study showed that <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2442 accumulated low, extracellular concentrations of gluconate and 2-ketogluconate when grown on glucose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. <italic>P. putida </italic>metabolizes glucose exclusively via the Entner-Doudoroff pathway in which 6-phosphogluconate is the key intermediate. This compound is produced by three convergent pathways; the glucokinase branch, the gluconokinase branch, and the 2-ketogluconate loop (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>)[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>]. The latter two pathways produce gluconate and 2-ketogluconate as intermediate compounds of the glucose catabolism. <italic>i</italic>JN746 accounts for these alternate routes and corresponding transport reactions for gluconate and 2-ketogluconate.</p><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Glucose metabolizing pathways present in <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 and its metabolic reconstruction, <italic>i</italic>JN746.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-3"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Comparison of growth performance of the <italic>in silico </italic>strain <italic>i</italic>JN746 and KT2442.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Strain</bold><break/></td><td align="center"><bold>Carbon </bold><break/><bold>source</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>&#x003bc;max(h<sup>-1</sup>) </bold><break/><bold>iJN746</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>&#x003bc;max(h<sup>-1</sup>) </bold><break/><bold>KT2442</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Carbon Uptake rate </bold><break/><bold>(mmol gDW/h)</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>O<sub>2 </sub>Uptake rate </bold><break/><bold>(mmol gDW/h)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center"><italic>i</italic>JN746/KT2442</td><td align="center">Glucose</td><td align="center">0.751</td><td align="center">0.56a</td><td align="center">6.3a</td><td align="center">15.34d</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>i</italic>JN746/KT2442</td><td align="center">Toluene</td><td align="center">0.421</td><td align="center">0.72b</td><td align="center">11.9b</td><td align="center">18.5c</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>i</italic>JN746/KT2442</td><td align="center">Toluene</td><td align="center">0.476</td><td align="center">0.72</td><td align="center">11.9</td><td align="center">20.93d</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>i</italic>JN746/KT2442</td><td align="center">Toluene</td><td align="center">0.7255</td><td align="center">0.72</td><td align="center">11.9</td><td align="center">33</td></tr><tr><td align="center"><italic>i</italic>JN746/KT2442</td><td align="center">Toluene</td><td align="center">1.262</td><td align="center">0.72</td><td align="center">11.9</td><td align="center">&#x0221e;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Comparison of growth performance of the <italic>in silico </italic>strain <italic>i</italic>JN746 and KT2442. The <italic>in silico </italic>growth rate was calculated in <italic>i</italic>M9 minimal medium plus glucose or toluene. Due to candidate oxygen limited growth in toluene, the <italic>in silico </italic>growth rate was calculated under different oxygen uptake rates In addition <italic>i</italic>JN746 growth in toluene as only carbon source was simulated at different oxygen uptake rates. <sup>a </sup>from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]; <sup>b </sup>from[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]; <sup>c </sup>from [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>], and <sup>d </sup>experimentally determined in this study.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Growth on Toluene</title><p>Aromatic compounds such as toluene or xylene are found in polluted soil. Some <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>species are known to grow on these compounds as a sole carbon source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>], making them interesting candidates for bioremediation of contaminated areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>]. As indicated above, <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 can metabolize various aromatic acids, amino acids, sugars, organic acids, fatty acids, and organo-sulfur compounds (see Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). More specifically, <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 degrades many aromatic compounds into a limited number of intermediates using a few catabolic pathways that were captured in <italic>i</italic>JN746 (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). In particular, the toluene biodegradation pathway has been extensively studied in <italic>P. putida </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>] and its genetic regulation is well known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>]. In this study, we assessed the capability of <italic>i</italic>JN746 to quantitatively predict aerobic growth on toluene (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The comparison showed a much lower <italic>in silico </italic>growth rate when compared to <italic>in vivo </italic>data, 0.421 versus 0.72 (60%) (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). In the following, we used different mathematical tools to elucidate reasons for this significant discrepancy.</p><sec><title>Reduced cost of toluene catabolism</title><p>Linear Programming (LP) problems have two parameters, shadow price and reduced cost, which can be used to characterize the optimal solution. While shadow prices are associated with each network metabolite, reduced costs are associated with each network reaction. The reduced cost signifies the amount by which the objective function (e.g. growth rate) would increase when the flux rate through a chosen reaction was increased by a single unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. Analyses of the reduced costs associated with uptake rates in the oxygen-limited toluene simulations identified the OUR as the only non-zero reduced cost value, 0.021 g biomass/gDW/h. This value corresponds to an increase of the OUR to 33 mmol oxygen/gDW/h to achieve the experimentally determined growth rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. At an OUR higher than 62 mmol oxygen/gDW/h oxygen is no longer a growth-limiting factor but toluene is. Note that the upper limit of 18.5 mmol oxygen/gDW/h for the OUR was taken from measurements for <italic>E. coli </italic>corresponding to the normal oxygen diffusion rate under atmospheric oxygen conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>]. Mathematically, the reduced cost analysis supports the hypothesis that oxygen is the limiting factor for toluene catabolism and hence causes the reduced <italic>in silico </italic>growth rate.</p></sec><sec><title>Phase Plane Analysis of toluene catabolism and oxygen uptake</title><p>We performed a phase plane analysis to further elucidate the correlation between toluene uptake, OUR, and biomass production rate (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>). We analyzed all four cases listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref> and found a direct effect of increased OUR on the toluene uptake capability and biomass production rate (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>). The experimentally observed growth rate of 0.72 &#x003bc;max(h<sup>-1</sup>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] was achieved by TUR ranging from 6 to 11.9 mmol toluene/gDW/h and OUR higher than 33 mmol oxygen/gDW/h. Note that a higher toluene uptake rate (TUR) requires a higher OUR (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4A</xref>), which indicates that the removal of intracellular oxygen was dependent on toluene availability. In fact, the three oxidative reactions involved in the conversion of toluene to 2-hydroxymuconate semialdehyde (toluene monooxygenase, benzoate 1,2-dioxygenase and catechol 2,3-dioxygenase) were found to have the higher flux rates besides the flux through the cytochrome C oxidase, an enzyme of the oxidative phosphorylation (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4B</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p><bold>(A) </bold><bold>The phenotypic phase plane analysis showed growth rate as a function of OUR and TUR in </bold><italic><bold>i</bold></italic><bold>JN746.</bold> The growth rate is given in 1/h (color legend). The red and yellow lines represent OUR constrained to 20.93 and 33 mmol/gDW/h, respectively. <bold>(B) </bold>Diagram of oxygen producing and reducing reactions in <italic>i</italic>JN746. The flux rates are given in mmol/gDW/h and represent one possible flux state of the network in toluene minimal medium at an OUR of 40 mmol oxygen/gDW/h. The reaction abbreviations are as follows: CAT, catalase; O2tpp, oxygen periplasmic transport (oxygen uptake); ASPO6, L-aspartate oxidase; BZ12DOX, benzoate 1,2-dioxygenase; CAT23DOX, catechol 2,3-dioxygenase; CYTBO3_4pp, cytochrome oxidase bo3; DHORD, dihydoorotic acid dehydrogenase; GLYCTO1, Glycolate oxidase and XMO, toluene monooxygenase.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-4"/></fig><p>In order to better understand this situation and since no detailed information about OUR was found for <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 under toluene-dependent growth conditions, we carried out <italic>in vivo </italic>experiments to determine the OUR of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 harboring the TOL plasmid (see Methods). As expected, the OUR in toluene growing cells was higher than glucose or octanoate growing cells; 20.93 compared to 15.34 and 14.88 mmol oxygen/gDW/h, respectively (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). The measured OUR uptake rate for growth in toluene did not explain the high oxygen requirement of the model, but clearly indicates the importance of oxygen uptake in toluene metabolism. Also, the measured OUR was slightly higher than the <italic>E. coli </italic>value that was used for the standard <italic>in silico </italic>simulations (20.93 vs. 18.5 mmol oxygen/gDW/h). In fact, oxygen dependent growth of toluene grown cells has been described for other <italic>P. putida </italic>strains. For example, Alagappan and Cowan reported a 10&#x000d7; higher oxygen-half saturation of <italic>P. putida </italic>F1 grown on toluene than other aerobic organisms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>]. Furthermore, the oxidative stress caused by toluene and other aromatic acids in the degradative process is well known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>]; however, this phenomenon was found to be mainly caused by reactive oxygen species due to incomplete oxygen reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>], indicating an active oxygen metabolism under this growth condition. Oxygen-limiting growth conditions were also reported for <italic>P. putida </italic>when grown on octanoate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>].</p><p>Taken together, our analysis suggests that the current <italic>P. putida </italic>metabolic network is incomplete. In fact, the current information and results suggest that the network is missing one or more reactions enabling a more oxygen-efficient catabolism of toluene and other highly reduced carbon sources (e.g. other aromatic compounds or fatty acids). This analysis represents a nice example of the broad range of applications for which <italic>i</italic>JN746 can be used to evaluate the consistency of experimental data and <italic>in silico </italic>prediction. <italic>i</italic>JN746 can serve as a platform to derive hypotheses about metabolic capabilities or missing functions in the network which can be ultimately tested in the laboratory. Hence, the metabolic reconstruction can help to increase our understanding and knowledge about this biotechnologically important organism.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Gene essentiality analysis in <italic>i</italic>JN746</title><p><italic>i</italic>JN746 was used as a framework to analyze candidate essential genes in <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 in LB rich medium. Therefore, the network reaction(s) associated with each gene was individually "deleted" by setting the flux to 0 and optimizing for the biomass function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. We wished to compare the <italic>in silico </italic>essentiality predictions with experimental data to assess the predictive potential of the model. However, no large-scale, experimental gene essentiality data are available for <italic>P. putida</italic>; the information can only be found for its phylogenetic relative <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>PAO1 and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>PA14 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. A recently published comparison between the <italic>P. putida </italic>and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>PAO1 genomes identified 3,143 potential orthologous pairs corresponding to 60% of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s total ORFs, as well as large sections of conserved gene order (synteny) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Therefore, we decided to compare our <italic>in silico </italic>single gene deletion results with the 335 essential metabolic and non-metabolic genes of <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. About 12% (92) of the 746 metabolic genes present in <italic>i</italic>JN746 were predicted to be essential in <italic>i</italic>LB medium [see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>]. A total of 53% (48) of these predicted essential genes in <italic>i</italic>JN746 agreed with essential genes of <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>]. More importantly, the 44 genes wrongly predicted as essential genes represent excellent targets for further refinement and expansion of the metabolism of <italic>i</italic>JN746 [see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref>] as has been done for <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>].</p><sec><title>False-positive predictions</title><p>The disagreement between the experimental and computational results can reveal possible errors in the experimental data as well as in the reconstructed network. The disagreements might be caused by low experimental or sequence evidences, each of which would have hindered the inclusion of the information into the reconstruction. For example, the <italic>fabB </italic>gene was predicted to be only essential in <italic>i</italic>JN746; however, after carrying out a detailed search on <italic>Pseudomona's </italic>genomes using "The <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>Genome Database V2" <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.Pseudomonas.com/"/> we found putative ORFs in the KT2440 and PA01 genome. These ORFs were annotated as alternative loci that could substitute a <italic>fabB </italic>deletion. Both, <italic>P. putida </italic>and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>have one copy of the <italic>fabB </italic>gene encoding for the 3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier-protein)synthase I (PP_4175 and PA1609, respectively). In addition, both strains have a copy of the <italic>fabF </italic>gene encoding for the 3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier-protein) synthase II (PP_1916 (40.92% identity with <italic>fabB</italic>-<sub>KT </sub>gene) and PA2965 (42.34% identity with <italic>fabB</italic>-<sub>PAO1 </sub>gene). Moreover, in the <italic>P. putida </italic>and <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>genome, some ORFs were annotated putatively to encode for a 3-oxoacyl-(acyl-carrier-protein) synthase II (PP_3303 (35.94% identity) and PP_2780 (27.32% identity) in KT2440, and PA_1373 (36.17% identity) in PAO1 strain. These putative ORFs were not included in <italic>i</italic>JN746 due to the lack of supporting evidence for their metabolic function, but this analysis showed that i) PAO1 has an isozyme present in its genome, and ii) KT2440 is very likely to have at least one other ORF encoding this or a similar function. In a similar way, the discrepancy between <italic>in silico </italic>essentiality prediction and <italic>in vitro </italic>observation for <italic>msbA </italic>gene could be explained. The gene product of <italic>msbA </italic>encodes for a transporter of phosphatidylethanolamine, which is known to have a genetic redundancy in <italic>Pseudomonas sp</italic>. taking into account the <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>annotation present in "The <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>Genome Database V2". However, the supporting evidence for alternative ORFs was not strong enough to be included into <italic>i</italic>JN746.</p><p>Finally, 37 genes were not predicted to be essential in <italic>i</italic>JN746 but they were reported as essential genes in <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>] [see Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>]. Of these false negatives, 13 genes encode for tRNAs synthetases which are typically included into metabolic networks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>] but are not functionally connected to the rest of the network. Hence, this disagreement was expected. Four additional false negative predictions, namely <italic>glyA </italic>(PP_0322 or PP_0671), <italic>fold </italic>(PP_1945 or PP_2265), <italic>fabZ </italic>(PP_4174 or PP_1602), and <italic>pyrH </italic>(PP_1771 or 1593), have at least one isozyme in KT2440 which were also accounted for in <italic>i</italic>JN746. For many remaining incorrectly predicted non-essential genes, the <italic>in silico </italic>deletion had a significant effect on the growth rate, reflecting their important roles in <italic>i</italic>JN746 metabolism [see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S5">5</xref>].</p><p>In general, many of these discrepancies suggest that metabolites enabling growth in the knock-outs might be imported from the external rich media since the exact composition of LB medium is not known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>]. This observation indicates the importance of using well defined minimal media in the experimental <italic>in vivo </italic>or <italic>in vitro </italic>procedure to enable the usage of the generated data for <italic>in silico </italic>predictions and comparison.</p></sec><sec><title>Gene essentiality and amino acid auxotrophy</title><p>Jacobs <italic>et al</italic>. reported a detailed amino acid auxotroph study in <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>PA01 using a minimal medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. We carried out another single gene deletion study in glucose <italic>i</italic>M9 medium and compared the results with this PA01 study. Here, we found an absolute agreement between <italic>in vivo </italic>and <italic>in silico </italic>gene essentiality for six amino acids, namely arginine, histidine, isoleucine, valine, leucine, and tryptophan (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). The presence of alternative loci in <italic>i</italic>JN746 explains partial disagreement for <italic>argA</italic>, <italic>argE</italic>, <italic>ilvA</italic>, and <italic>argJ</italic>. In fact, genetic redundancy for these genes was reported in <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. This high correlation between <italic>in silico </italic>and <italic>in vivo </italic>data shows the utility of this approach when you take into account metabolic or anabolic reactions in a well defined minimal media. The complete lists of potential essential genes predicted in glucose <italic>i</italic>M9 medium are listed in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S6">6</xref>.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The comparison of the <italic>in silico </italic>gene essentiality and experimental <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>data are shown under various amino acid auxotrophic conditions.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><td align="center"><bold>Amino acid</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>PP gene</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>gene</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>Reaction</bold></td><td align="center"><bold>iJN746/PA01&#x020ac; (growth)</bold></td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="center">Arginine</td><td align="center">PP_5185(PP_1346)</td><td align="center">argA&#x02020;,(argJ)</td><td align="center">ACGS,(ORNTAC, ACGS)</td><td align="center">(+/-)*</td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_5289</td><td align="center">argB</td><td align="center">ACGK</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_3633</td><td align="center">argC</td><td align="center">AGPR</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_5186,(PP_1346)</td><td align="center">argE&#x02020;,(argJ)</td><td align="center">ACODA(ORNTAC, ACGS)</td><td align="center">(+/-)*</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1088</td><td align="center">argG</td><td align="center">ARGSS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0184</td><td align="center">argH</td><td align="center">ARGSL</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1346</td><td align="center">argJ&#x02020;</td><td align="center">ORNTAC, ACGS</td><td align="center">(+/-)*</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Histidine</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0292</td><td align="center">hisA</td><td align="center">PRMICIi</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0289</td><td align="center">hisB</td><td align="center">IGPDH</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0967</td><td align="center">hisC</td><td align="center">HSTPTr</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0966</td><td align="center">hisD</td><td align="center">HISTD</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_5015</td><td align="center">hisE</td><td align="center">PRATPP</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0293</td><td align="center">hisF</td><td align="center">IG3PS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0965</td><td align="center">hisG</td><td align="center">ATPPRTr</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0290</td><td align="center">hisH</td><td align="center">IG3PS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_5014</td><td align="center">hisI</td><td align="center">PRAMPC</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Isoleucine-valine</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_3446, PP5149</td><td align="center">ilvA-1, ilvA-2</td><td align="center">SER_AL, THRD_L</td><td align="center">(+/-)*</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_4680</td><td align="center">ilvB (ilvI)&#x000a3;</td><td align="center">ACHBS, ACLS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_4678</td><td align="center">ilvC</td><td align="center">KARA1, KARA2</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_5128</td><td align="center">ilvD</td><td align="center">DHAD1, DHAD2</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_3511</td><td align="center">ilvE</td><td align="center">VALTA, LEUTA, ILETA</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_4679</td><td align="center">ilvN(ilvH)&#x000a3;</td><td align="center">ACHBS, ACLS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Leucine</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1025</td><td align="center">leuA</td><td align="center">IPPS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1988</td><td align="center">leuB</td><td align="center">IPMDr</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1985</td><td align="center">leuC</td><td align="center">IPPMIa, IPPMIb</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1986</td><td align="center">leuD</td><td align="center">IPPMIa, IPPMIb</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td align="center">Tryptophan</td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="1"><hr></hr></td><td></td><td></td><td></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0082</td><td align="center">trpA</td><td align="center">TRPS1r, TRPS3r</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0083</td><td align="center">trpB</td><td align="center">TRPS2, TRPS1r</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0422</td><td align="center">trpC</td><td align="center">IGPS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0421</td><td align="center">trpD</td><td align="center">ANPRT</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0417</td><td align="center">trpE</td><td align="center">ANS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_1995</td><td align="center">trpF</td><td align="center">PRAI</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr><tr><td></td><td align="center">PP_0420</td><td align="center">trpG</td><td align="center">ANS</td><td align="center">(-/-)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The comparison of the <italic>in silico </italic>gene essentiality and experimental <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>data are shown under various amino acid auxotrophic conditions. The <italic>in silico </italic>mutants were grown on Glucose-iM9 medium. * No auxotrophy was detected in <italic>i</italic>JN746, genetic redundancy for these genes was reported in <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>species. In <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>mutants for orthologous genes, a significant residual growth on minimal medium was shown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. &#x000a3; Alternative name in <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>. &#x020ac; From [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>].</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec><title><italic>i</italic>JN746 as a cell factory</title><p>In the previous section, we used the metabolic reconstruction to assess the current knowledge of <italic>P. putida's </italic>metabolism by comparing and testing <italic>in silico </italic>predictions with physiological data. However, metabolic network reconstructions can also serve as engineering and design tools [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>] in addition to their use for discovery purposes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. Here, we investigate the poly-3-hydroxyalkanoate (PHA) production capability by the metabolic network. PHAs are a class of microbially produced polyesters that have the potential to replace conventional, petrochemically derived plastics in packaging and coating applications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. The biotechnological interest originates from their biodegradability and the broad range of physical properties depending on the number of carbons and side chains present in the PHA polymers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. These polymers are stored by many microorganisms under inorganic nutrient limited and carbon-excess growth conditions and are used as carbon- and energy sources under starvation conditions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. The medium-side-chain PHAs (msc-PHAs) are composed of C<sub>6 </sub>to C<sub>16 </sub>3-hydroxy fatty acids and are commonly produced by fluorescent <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>. In this way, <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 is an excellent candidate for msc-PHA production studies, since i) the basic msc-PHA production processes in KT2440 are well known [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>], ii) its genome is completely sequenced, iii) KT2440 has a well known metabolic versatility (can use a large list of carbon source as PHA precursors), iv) it is a very good host-vector biosafety system for gene cloning and expression of heterologous genes and v) this strain has been used in numerous biotechnology processes including msc-PHA production.</p><p><italic>i</italic>JN746 accounts for msc-PHAs ranging from C<sub>6 </sub>to C<sub>14</sub>, including two unsaturated msc-PHAs and a mixed msc-PHA polymer consisting of C<sub>8 </sub>to C<sub>12 </sub>chains. We tested the msc-PHA production capability of <italic>i</italic>JN746 from the different carbon- and energy sources listed in Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>. All carbon sources were found to result in msc-PHA production under the chosen simulation condition (dilution rate of 0.2 hr<sup>-1</sup>). Many of these metabolites have been reported to yield in PHA production in <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>[see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>] although many studies focused on fatty acid or carbohydrate derived msc-PHAs. In general, it is assumed that carbon sources generating high levels of acetyl-CoA are good candidates for PHA production [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Therefore, it was not surprising to find fatty acids and carbohydrates as the best PHA precursors in <italic>i</italic>JN746 as well (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). The list of candidate (<italic>in silico</italic>) precursors includes i) L-branched-chain amino acids (L-leucine, L-isoleucine, L-Valine etc), ii) some aromatic compounds metabolized via &#x003b2;-ketoadipate pathway (catechol, p-coumarate, etc), and iii) other (phenylacetic acid or glycerol) (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). Interestingly, phenylacetic acid and glycerol have been reported as excellent precursors for PHA [Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>]. In fact, a recent study showed that <italic>P. putida </italic>CA3 can accumulate 0.17 g of PHA per g of phenylacetate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>].</p><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p><bold>Maximal possible msc-PHA production rate from various carbon sources</bold>. The msc-PHA production rate is scaled per substrate carbon to facilitate the yield comparison. The simulation conditions correspond to chemostate culturing at a dilution rate of &#x003bc; = 0.2 1/hr, minimal medium (iM9) supplemented with each carbon source. 'Mix' corresponds to the simultaneous production of C8:0, C6:0, C10:0, and C12:0 msc-PHA (1:1:1:1).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-5"/></fig><p>Fatty acids resulted in the highest PHA production rate overall and when scaled per carbons (see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>, and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>). In fact, fatty acids are converted into msc-PHAs quickly via &#x003b2;-oxidation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Experimental studies showed that the resulting msc-PHA-monomers have the same or a smaller number of carbons as the fatty acids from which they are derived [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>]. In contrast, in the model, higher carbon msc-PHAs could be formed since the current model formulation does not exclude simultaneous fatty acid synthesis and &#x003b2;-oxidation. This situation has been experimentally demonstrated using hexanoate as a msc-PHA precursor. Huijberts <italic>et al</italic>. used inhibitors of fatty acid metabolism and demonstrated that, depending on the nature of the substrate, precursors for PHA synthesis could be derived from either beta-oxidation or fatty acid biosynthesis, and interestingly, when hexanoate was used as carbon source for msc-PHA accumulation, both routes can operate simultaneously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. On the other hand, the carbohydrates are converted into msc-PHA from intermediates of the fatty acid synthesis and have been shown to result primarily in C<sub>8 </sub>and C<sub>10 </sub>monomers. The model, in contrast, is able to produce the full range of msc-PHAs from carbohydrates (Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref>). These discrepancies suggest that despite broad specificity of the Poly-(3-hydroxyalkanoate) polymerase, ranging from C<sub>6 </sub>to C<sub>16 </sub>3-hydroxy fatty acids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], the PHA polymerizing enzyme system might have preferences for monomers with 8 or 10 carbon atoms, while larger and smaller monomers are incorporated less efficiently. This fact can also explain why, during growth on hexanoate, msc-PHA precursors are synthesized by elongation and <italic>de novo </italic>fatty acid synthesis pathway, resulting more preferably in the generation of C8 and C10 monomers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Such differences in specific activity could be applied as additional constraints to the model to obtain similar results as those observed experimentally.</p><p>Taken together, this example illustrates how <italic>i</italic>JN746 could be employed as a tool to identify new substrates (catechol, p-coumarate, isoleucine etc) for production of the different msc-PHA monomers or msc-PHA mixtures. Furthermore, computational tools such as OptKnock[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>] or OptStrain[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>] could help to design i) higher production strains, and/or ii) couple PHA production to growth rate. Such approaches have proven successful for other metabolic engineering designs such as lactate production in <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>] or succinate production in <italic>M. succiniciproducens </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Here, we presented the first genome-scale reconstruction of <italic>P. putida</italic>, a biotechnologically interesting all-surrounder.<italic> i</italic>JN746 is a highly detailed reconstruction of the <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 metabolic network that captures the important biotechnological capabilities, such as biodegradation of aromatic compounds, of this paradigmatic bacterium. Moreover, <italic>i</italic>JN746 represents a comprehensive knowledge base summarizing and categorizing the information currently available for <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440. This study evaluated the metabolic network content and showed some examples of how <italic>i</italic>JN746 could be used for biotechnological purposes. Taken together, our results underlined the value of <italic>i</italic>JN746 as a suitable tool to study of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolism and its biotechnical applications by the <italic>P. putida </italic>community.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><sec><title><italic>In vivo </italic>determination of oxygen consumption and cell culture condition</title><p><italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 harboring the TOL plasmid was used for <italic>in vivo </italic>determination of oxygen consumption experiments. The bacterium was grown at 30&#x000b0;C in M9 minimal medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>] with octanoate (15 mM), glucose (0.3% [wt/vol]), or toluene (6 mM) as a carbon source. Liquid cultures were agitated on a gyratory shaker operated at 250 rpm. For the OUR experiment, an overnight culture of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 strain grown in each carbon source was diluted until the turbidity at 600 nm (OD<sub>600</sub>) was 0.05 in fresh M9 minimal medium with the appropriate carbon source, samples were then incubated until the culture reached a turbidity at 600 nm of 0.6 for glucose or octanoate growing cells and 0.45 in toluene growing cells. Aliquots of 2 ml were taken for OUR determination; the cells were harvested by centrifugation, washed twice and re-suspended in 1 ml of fresh medium containing the appropriate carbon source using the above concentrations. The OUR was measured by monitoring the substrate-dependent oxygen consumption rate at 30&#x000b0;C using an oxygen electrode (DW1 Hansa-Tech Oxygen Electrode, Hansa-Tech Oxygen Instrument Limited) in 1-ml assay mixture. Cellular dry weight (CDW) was determined using previously published methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>], using at least 3 parallel 10-ml cell suspensions that were harvested by centrifugation at 15,800 &#x000d7; <italic>g</italic>. The pellets were washed with 0.9% NaCl and then dried at 105&#x000b0;C for 24 h to a constant weight using pre-dried and weighed 2-ml Eppendorf cups.</p></sec><sec><title>Network reconstruction</title><p>The reconstruction process was done as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Briefly, the genome annotation of <italic>P. putida </italic>KT2440 was obtained from TIGR (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cmr.tigr.org/tigr-scripts/CMR/GenomePage.cgi?org=gpp"/>, 06/27/2007) and was used as the framework of the network reconstruction. <italic>P. putida</italic>-specific primary and review literature and books were used to retrieve information about every network reaction: i) substrate specificity, ii) coenzyme specificity, iii) reaction directionality, iv) enzyme and reaction localization, and v) <underline>g</underline>ene-<underline>p</underline>rotein-<underline>r</underline>eaction (GPR) association. Relevant references were associated with every network reaction [see Additional files <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>]. Public databases such as KEGG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>], PSEUDOCYC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B58">58</xref>], and SYSTOMONAS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>] were used when no literature evidence could be found for the previous reaction characteristics. Spontaneous reactions were included into the reconstruction if i) physiological evidence suggested their presence (e.g., the presence of at least the substrate or product in the reconstruction); and ii) textbooks or KEGG [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>] suggested the existence of such reactions. Every network reaction was mass- and charge balanced assuming an intracellular pH of 7.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Note that this mass- and charge balancing also included balancing the network reactions for protons (H<sup>+</sup>), water (H<sub>2</sub>O), and various co-factors (e.g., adenosine triphosphate (ATP)). No gene-associated reactions were included when no corresponding gene was annotated in <italic>P. putida</italic>'s genome but physiological or experimental data supported the presence of the biochemical transformation being part of <italic>P. putida</italic>'s metabolism. Finally the reversibility was determined from primary literature data for each particular enzyme/reaction, if available. This literature search resulted in a first manually-curated reconstruction specific to <italic>P. putida's </italic>metabolism based on genome annotation and available biochemical evidence. However, this list is normally incomplete and will contain network gaps that may need to be filled depending on supporting evidence. This step requires manual effort again by searching the scientific literature for supporting information. If no <italic>P. putida</italic>-specific experimental evidence could be found for a transport reaction or biochemical transformation of a metabolite, no reaction or transporter was added to the network. Finally, the network capabilities were evaluated and compared with experimental data as described in Reed et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>]. Detailed lists of the genes, proteins, and reactions are contained in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S8">8</xref>, and the definitions of all metabolites and their abbreviations are found in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref>.</p><p>SimPheny (Genomatica Inc., San Diego, CA) software was used for the reconstruction and gap evaluation process.</p></sec><sec><title>Conversion of the network reconstruction to a condition-specific model</title><p>The reconstructed metabolic network is often represented in a tabular format, listing all network reactions and metabolites in a human-readable manner along with confidence scores and comments (see Reed et al [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] for details). The conversion into a mathematical, or computer-readable format, can be done automatically by parsing the stoichiometric coefficients from the network reaction list (e.g. using the COBRA toolbox [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>]). The mathematical format is called a stoichiometric matrix, or S-matrix, where the rows correspond to the network metabolites and the columns represent the network reactions. For each reaction, the stoichiometric coefficients of the substrates are listed with a minus sign in the corresponding cell of the matrix, while the product coefficients are positive numbers, by definition. The resulting size of the S-matrix is m &#x000d7; n, where m is the number of metabolites and n the number of network reactions. Mathematically, the S-matrix is a linear transformation of the flux vector <italic>v </italic>= (<italic>v</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>v</italic><sub>2</sub>,.., <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>n</italic></sub>) to a vector of time derivatives of the concentration vector <italic>x </italic>= (<italic>x</italic><sub>1</sub>, <italic>x</italic><sub>2</sub>,.., <italic>x</italic><sub><italic>m</italic></sub>) as <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M1" name="1752-0509-2-79-i1" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></inline-formula>. At steady-state, the change in concentration as a function of time is zero; hence, it follows: <inline-formula><mml:math xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="M2" name="1752-0509-2-79-i1" overflow="scroll"><mml:semantics><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x022c5;</mml:mo><mml:mi>v</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:semantics></mml:math></inline-formula> = 0. The set of possible flux vectors v that satisfy this equality constraint might be subject to further constraints by defining <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02264; <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i </italic></sub>&#x02264; <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max </sub>for reaction <italic>i</italic>. In fact, for every irreversible network reaction <italic>i</italic>, the lower bound was defined as <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min </sub>&#x02265; 0 and the upper bound was defined as <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max </sub>&#x02265; 0.</p><p>Exchange reactions, which supply the network with nutrients or remove secretion products from the medium, were defined for all known medium components (see Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S9">9</xref> for details). The uptake of a substrate by the network was defined by a flux rate <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i </italic></sub>&#x0003c; 0 and secretion of a by-product was defined to be <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i </italic></sub>&#x0003e; 0 for every exchange reaction <italic>i</italic>. An exchange reaction is represented in the reaction is as follows: e.g. D-glucose exchange: Ex_glc-D: 1 glc-D &#x02192;. Note that this exchange reaction is unbalanced. Exchange (uptake) reactions define the presence of media components as if one would add metabolites into an <italic>in silico </italic>flask.</p><p>Finally, the application of constraints corresponding to different environmental conditions (e.g. minimal growth medium) or different genetic background (e.g. enzyme-deficient mutant) allow the transition from metabolic network reconstruction to condition-specific model. Note that the metabolic network reconstruction is unique to the target organism (and defined by its genome) while it can give rise to many different models by applying condition-specific constraints. All flux rates, <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>, except biomass formation, are given in mmol/gDW/h.</p></sec><sec><title>Biomass function</title><p>It is generally assumed that the objective of living organisms is to divide and proliferate. Subsequently, many metabolic network reconstructions have a so-called biomass function, in which all known metabolic precursors of cellular biomass are gathered (e.g. amino acids, nucleotides, phospholipids, vitamins, cofactors, energetic requirements etc.) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Since no detailed studies about <italic>P. putida's </italic>biomass composition are available, the biomass composition from <italic>E. coli </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>] was used as a template for <italic>i</italic>JN746's biomass function. However, data from <italic>P. putida </italic>were added, (e.g. membrane phospholipid composition [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>]), when available. The detailed calculation of the biomass composition is provided in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S10">10</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title><italic>in silico </italic>medium composition</title><p>Aerobic growth was modeled in two different culture media: <italic>in silico </italic>M9 minimal medium (<italic>i</italic>M9) and <italic>in silico </italic>Luria-Bertani medium (<italic>i</italic>LB) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>]. For <italic>i</italic>M9 simulation, and according to the well described M9 minimal medium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>], the following external metabolites, CO<sub>2</sub>, Co<sub>2 </sub><sup>+</sup>, Fe<sub>2 </sub><sup>+</sup>, H<sup>+</sup>, H<sub>2</sub>O, Na<sub>2 </sub><sup>+</sup>, Ni<sub>2 </sub><sup>+</sup>, NH<sub>4</sub>, P<sub>i </sub>and SO<sub>4 </sub>were allowed to enter and leave the network by setting the constraints on the corresponding exchange reactions (<italic>i</italic>) to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -10<sup>6 </sup>mmol/gDW/h and to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02264; 10<sup>6 </sup>mmol/gDW/h. The uptake rate for each carbon source was constrained to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -10 mmol/gDW/h and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02264; 0 mmol/gDW/h. The oxygen uptake rate (OUR) was limited to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -18.5 mmol/gDW/h (based on <italic>E. coli </italic>data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>]), if not noted differently. In each individual simulation, all other external metabolites were only allowed to leave the system by constraining their exchange fluxes <italic>i </italic>between <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; 0 and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02265; 10<sup>6 </sup>mmol/gDW/h. The <italic>i</italic>LB medium was based on the published analysis of yeast extract and tryptone provided by the corresponding manufactures, and the <italic>i</italic>LB simulations were performed according previously published methods [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Phenotypic phase-plane analysis</title><p>Phenotypic phase-plane analysis (PhPP) was carried out using SimPheny (Genomatica Inc., San Diego, CA). The underlying algorithm was described elsewhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. The simulation was carried out using <italic>i</italic>M9 minimal medium (as described above) and setting the bounds of toluene uptake between <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -11.9 mmol/gDW/h (based on measurement by [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>] and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02264; 0 mmol/gDW/h; and of oxygen between <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -160 mmol/gDW/h and <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02264; 0 mmol/gDW/h. The step size was chosen to be 35.</p></sec><sec><title>Reduced Cost</title><p>Reduced cost is a parameter of linear programming (LP) problems which is associated with each network reaction (<italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>) and represents the amount by which the objective function (e.g. growth rate) could be increased when the flux rate through this reaction was increased by a single unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. Reduced cost is often used to analyze the obtained optimal solution and evaluate alternate solutions from the original solution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B77">77</xref>]. In this study, we analyzed the reduced costs associated with uptake reactions to identify candidate reactions through which an increased flux would result in a higher growth rate (under the chosen simulation condition). The growth condition was <italic>i</italic>M9 medium with toluene as carbon source. The constraints were set as described above and linear programming was employed to solve the optimization problem (maximizing growth).</p></sec><sec><title>Gene essentiality and auxotrophy</title><p>In order to determine the effect of a single gene deletion, all the reactions associated with each gene in <italic>i</italic>JN746 were individually "deleted" by setting the flux to 0 and optimizing for the biomass function [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. A lethal deletion was defined if no positive flux value for the biomass function could be obtained for the given mutant <italic>in silico </italic>strain and medium. The simulations were performed using i) <italic>i</italic>LB rich medium for general gene essentially experiment and ii) glucose-iM9 minimal medium for auxotrophy experiments (See above). The glucose uptake rate was fixed to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min </sub>= <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max </sub>= -6.3 mmol/gDW/h in the latter study. OUR was set to be <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -18.5 mmol/gDW/h in both cases.</p></sec><sec><title>msc-PHA production</title><p>The msc-PHA production from each possible carbon source (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>) in <italic>i</italic>M9 medium was determined by setting the growth rate to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>growth</italic>,min </sub>= <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>growth</italic>,max </sub>0.2 gDW/gDW/h. The lower bound of each carbon uptake reaction was set to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -10 mmol/gDW/h and the upper bound was set to be <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,max</sub>&#x02264; 0 mmol/gDW/h. The lower bound of the oxygen uptake rate was set to <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>i</italic>,min</sub>&#x02265; -20 mmol/gDW/h for all simulations. In <italic>i</italic>JN746, six types of msc-PHAs are defined as well as msc-PHA compounds consisting of four different carbon chains [see Figure <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> and Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S7">7</xref>]. The corresponding demand functions were used as objective functions independently for the optimization problem. The resulting msc-PHA production rates were scaled by the number of carbons of the corresponding carbon sources to facilitate a yield comparison.</p></sec><sec><title>Software</title><p>All computational simulations were performed using Matlab (The MathWorks Inc., Natick, MA) if not stated otherwise. TomLab (Tomlab Optimization Inc., San Diego, CA) was used as linear programming solver. Optimization formulations and the gene deletion studies employed the Matlab-based COBRA toolbox [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Authors' contributions</title><p>All authors conceived the study. JN carried out the reconstruction of <italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>KT2440. JN and IT performed the analyses. JN, IT, BOP designed the study and wrote manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Table S1</bold>. Carbon, nitrogen, and sulfur sources, which enabled growth of <italic>i</italic>JN746.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S1.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Table S2</bold>. Essentials genes predicted correctly in <italic>i</italic>JN746 compared with experimental data of <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S2.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Figure S1</bold>. Schematic representation of <italic>in silico </italic>gene essentiality in <italic>i</italic>JN746 (<italic>i</italic>LB medium) compared experimental data of gene essentiality in <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>].</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S3.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4"><caption><title>Additional file 4</title><p><bold>Table S3</bold>. False-positive essential genes in <italic>i</italic>JN746 when compared with <italic>P. aeruginosa</italic>'s experimental data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>].</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S4.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S5"><caption><title>Additional file 5</title><p><bold>Table S4</bold>. False-negative essential genes in <italic>i</italic>JN746. Genes that were not predicted to be essential in <italic>i</italic>JN746 but were reported as essential genes in <italic>P. aeruginosa </italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>].</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S5.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S6"><caption><title>Additional file 6</title><p><bold>Table S5</bold>. Predicted essential genes in Glucose-<italic>i</italic>M9 minimal medium. Not shown are genes that were also predicted to be essential in <italic>i</italic>LB rich medium.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S6.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S7"><caption><title>Additional file 7</title><p><bold>Table S6</bold>. PHA polymer composition found in different <italic>Pseudomonas </italic>strains sorted by carbon sources.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S7.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S8"><caption><title>Additional file 8</title><p><bold>Table S7</bold>. List of metabolites in <italic>i</italic>JN746. The file contains a detail list of metabolites present in the metabolic reconstruction. The molecular formulae, the charge as well as the KeggID are shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S8.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S9"><caption><title>Additional file 9</title><p><bold>Table S8</bold>. List of the reactions contain in iJN746. The file details the reactions account in the metabolic reconstruction. The official name, the equation of the reaction, the subsystem, the EC number and de GPR association is shown.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S9.xls" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="vnd.ms-excel"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S10"><caption><title>Additional file 10</title><p><bold>Table S9</bold>. List of biomass components in <italic>i</italic>JN746. This file contains the complete list of compounds which are part of <italic>Pseudomonas putida </italic>biomass.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1752-0509-2-79-S10.doc" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank J.R. Luque-Ortega for help in the oxygen uptake experiments. We thank M. Abrahams, M. Mo, and S. Burning for critical reading of the manuscript. JN is grateful to T. Conrad for your help during the San Diego stay and E. D&#x000ed;az and M.A. Prieto for their valuable help and suggestion during the metabolic reconstruction. JN is the recipients of an I3P predoctoral Fellowship from the Consejo Superior de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas (CSIC) and JN stay in San Diego was supported by a short term I3P fellowship.</p></sec></ack><ref-list><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Richmond</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Genetics and Biochemistry of Pseudomonas</source><year>1975</year><publisher-name>New York, USA: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The metabolic versatility of pseudomonads</article-title><source>Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek</source><year>1982</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6808915</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00405197</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagdasarian</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagdasarian</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular and functional analysis of the TOL plasmid pWWO from Pseudomonas putida and cloning of genes for the entire regulated aromatic ring meta cleavage pathway</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1981</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>7458</fpage><lpage>7462</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6950388</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.78.12.7458</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bayley</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Duggleby</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Worsey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hardy</surname><given-names>KG</given-names></name><name><surname>Broda</surname><given-names>aP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two modes of loss of the Tol function from Pseudomonas putida mt-2</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1977</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>204</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">895716</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00330838</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mermod</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New route to bacterial production of indigo</article-title><source>Bio/Technology</source><year>1986</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>321</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt0486-321</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wasserfallen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Redesigning metabolic routes: manipulation of TOL plasmid pathway for catabolism of alkylbenzoates</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1987</year><volume>235</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3468623</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.3468623</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cases</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression systems and physiological control of promoter activity in bacteria</article-title><source>Curr Opin Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>303</fpage><lpage>310</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066491</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1369-5274(98)80034-9</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gilbert</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Keasling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A constructed microbial consortium for biodegradation of the organophosphorus insecticide parathion</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2003</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12658518</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Steffan</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Unterman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Designing microorganisms for the treatment of toxic wastes</article-title><source>Annu Rev Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>48</volume><fpage>525</fpage><lpage>557</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7826017</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.mi.48.100194.002521</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dejonghe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Boon</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Seghers</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Top</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioaugmentation of soils by increasing microbial richness: missing links</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11722545</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2001.00236.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gal&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Enhancing desulphurization by engineering a flavin reductase-encoding gene cassette in recombinant biocatalysts</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2000</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>669</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11214801</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2000.00151.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeyer</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lehrbach</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of cloned genes of Pseudomonas TOL plasmid to effect biotransformation of benzoates to cis-dihydrodiols and catechols by Escherichia coli cells</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1985</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1409</fpage><lpage>1413</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3911905</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wubbolts</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotransformation of substituted benzoates to the corresponding cis-diols by an engineered strain of Pseudomonas oleovorans producing the TOL plasmid-specified enzyme toluate-1,2-dioxygenase</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>569</fpage><lpage>571</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2306096</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dordick</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiener</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wubbolts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Witholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Industrial biocatalysis today and tomorrow</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2001</year><volume>409</volume><fpage>258</fpage><lpage>268</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11196655</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35051736</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olivera</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name><name><surname>Carnicero</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Jodra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Minambres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Abraham</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gallardo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Naharro</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Genetically engineered Pseudomonas: a factory of new bioplastics with broad applications</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11722541</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2001.00224.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ouyang</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chung</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>GQ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of Polyhydroxyalkanoates with High 3-Hydroxydodecanoate Monomer Content by fadB and fadA Knockout Mutant of Pseudomonas putida KT2442</article-title><source>Biomacromolecules</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>2504</fpage><lpage>2511</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17661516</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/bm0702307</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huijberts</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Witholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas putida KT2442 cultivated on glucose accumulates poly(3-hydroxyalkanoates) consisting of saturated and unsaturated monomers</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1992</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>536</fpage><lpage>544</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1610179</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Sullivan</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Gara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traits of fluorescent Pseudomonas spp. involved in suppression of plant root pathogens</article-title><source>Microbiol Rev</source><year>1992</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>662</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1480114</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>UF</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrissey</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Gara</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pseudomonas for biocontrol of phytopathogens: from functional genomics to commercial exploitation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2001</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>295</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11404107</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0958-1669(00)00212-3</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Paulsen</surname><given-names>IT</given-names></name><name><surname>Dodson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hilbert</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins dos Santos</surname><given-names>VAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Fouts</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Pop</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Complete genome sequence and comparative analysis of the metabolically versatile Pseudomonas putida KT2440</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>799</fpage><lpage>808</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12534463</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2002.00366.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pseudomonas</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>New York Kluwer: Academic/Plenum Publishers</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yuste</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hervas</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Canosa</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Perez</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Santero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Growth phase-dependent expression of the Pseudomonas putida KT2440 transcriptional machinery analysed with a genome-wide DNA microarray</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>177</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16343331</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2005.00890.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dominguez-Cuevas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez-Pastor</surname><given-names>J-E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional Tradeoff between Metabolic and Stress-response Programs in Pseudomonas putida KT2440 Cells Exposed to Toluene</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2006</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>11981</fpage><lpage>11991</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16495222</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M509848200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Young Hwan</given-names></name><name><surname>Sung-Ho</surname><given-names>Kun Cho</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>Yun Jin</given-names></name><name><surname>Kyung-Hoon</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>Kwon Jong</given-names></name><name><surname>YSI</surname><given-names>Kim</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of aromatic catabolic pathways in Pseudomonas putida KT 2440 using a combined proteomic approach: 2-DE/MS and cleavable isotope-coded affinity tag analysis</article-title><source>PROTEOMICS</source><year>2006</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1301</fpage><lpage>1318</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16470664</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pmic.200500329</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>del Castillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez-Herva</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Duque</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Convergent Peripheral Pathways Catalyze Initial Glucose Catabolism in Pseudomonas putida: Genomic and Flux Analysis</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>5142</fpage><lpage>5152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17483213</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00203-07</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>del Castillo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous Catabolite Repression between Glucose and Toluene Metabolism in Pseudomonas putida Is Channeled through Different Signaling Pathways</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>6602</fpage><lpage>6610</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17616587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.00679-07</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jimenez</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Minambres</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genomic analysis of the aromatic catabolic pathways from Pseudomonas putida KT2440</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2002</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>824</fpage><lpage>841</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12534466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1462-2920.2002.00370.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>dos Santos</surname><given-names>VAPM</given-names></name><name><surname>Heim</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>ERB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights into the genomic basis of niche specificity of Pseudomonas putida KT2440</article-title><source>Environmental Microbiology</source><year>2004</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1264</fpage><lpage>1286</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15560824</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1462-2920.2004.00734.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B&#x000d8;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico biotechnology. Era of reconstruction and interrogation</article-title><source>Curr Opin Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>51</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15102466</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.copbio.2004.01.006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Famili</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards multidimensional genome annotation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two-dimensional annotation of genomes</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2004</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1218</fpage><lpage>1219</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15470454</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1004-1218</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale models of microbial cells: evaluating the consequences of constraints</article-title><source>Nat Rev Micro</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>886</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrgard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative Prediction of Cellular Metabolism with Constraint-based Models: The COBRA Toolbox</article-title><source>Nat Protoc</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17406635</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.99</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale models of microbial cells: evaluating the consequences of constraints</article-title><source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source><year>2004</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>886</fpage><lpage>897</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15494745</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro1023</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scholten</surname><given-names>JCM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Brockman</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ideker</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling methanogenesis with a genome-scale metabolic reconstruction of Methanosarcina barkeri</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>2</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16738551</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Krummenacker</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Broadbelt</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hatzimanikatis</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A genome-scale metabolic reconstruction for Escherichia coli K-12 MG1655 that accounts for 1260 ORFs and thermodynamic information</article-title><source>Mol Syst Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>3</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17593909</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oh</surname><given-names>Y-K</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale Reconstruction of Metabolic Network in Bacillus subtilis Based on High-throughput Phenotyping and Gene Essentiality Data</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>282</volume><fpage>28791</fpage><lpage>28799</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17573341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M703759200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An Expanded Metabolic Reconstruction of Helicobacter pylori (<italic>i</italic>IT341 GSM/GPR): An <italic>in silico </italic>genome-scale characterization of single and double deletion mutants</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>5818</fpage><lpage>5830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16077130</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.16.5818-5830.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigating the metabolic capabilities of Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Rv using the in silico strain iNJ661 and proposing alternative drug targets</article-title><source>BMC Systems Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17555602</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1752-0509-1-26</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beste</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hooper</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonde</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Avignone-Rossa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushell</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Klamt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kierzek</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>McFadden</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GSMN-TB: a web-based genome-scale network model of Mycobacterium tuberculosis metabolism</article-title><source>Genome Biol</source><year>2007</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>R89</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2007-8-5-r89</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-scale reconstruction of the metabolic network in Staphylococcus aureus N315: an initial draft to the two-dimensional annotation</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>8</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15752426</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-5-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kummel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruinatscha</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Panke</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico genome-scale reconstruction and validation of the Staphylococcus aureus metabolic network</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2005</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>864</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16155945</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.20663</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Forster</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Modeling Lactococcus lactis using a genome-scale flux model</article-title><source>BMC Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>39</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15982422</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2180-5-39</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duarte</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Srivas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global reconstruction of the human metabolic network based on genomic and bibliomic data</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>1777</fpage><lpage>1782</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610772104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Applebee</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Herring</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bui</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems approach to refining genome annotation</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>17480</fpage><lpage>17484</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0603364103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli </italic>K-12 undergoes adaptive evolution to achieve <italic>in silico </italic>predicted optimal growth</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>420</volume><fpage>186</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12432395</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01149</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive Evolution of <italic>E. coli </italic>on Either Lactate or Glycerol Leads to Convergent, Generalist Phenotypes</article-title><source>International E Coli Alliance Second Annual Meeting: 2004; Banff, Alberta</source><year>2004</year></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic gene deletion strains of Escherichia coli evolve to computationally predicted growth phenotypes</article-title><source>Nature Genetics</source><year>2004</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1058</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15448692</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng1432</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>KH</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic engineering of Escherichia coli for the production of L-valine based on transcriptome analysis and in silico gene knockout simulation</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2007</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>7797</fpage><lpage>7802</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0702609104</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Candidate metabolic network states in human mitochondria: Impact of diabetes, ischemia, and diet</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>11683</fpage><lpage>11695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15572364</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M409072200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ravasz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Somera</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mongru</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barabasi</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hierarchical organization of modularity in metabolic networks</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2002</year><volume>297</volume><fpage>1551</fpage><lpage>1555</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12202830</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1073374</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barabasi</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Network biology: understanding the cell's functional organization</article-title><source>Nature reviews</source><year>2004</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14735121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1272</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almaas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Vicsek</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltvai</surname><given-names>ZN</given-names></name><name><surname>Barabasi</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global organization of metabolic fluxes in the bacterium <italic>Escherichia coli</italic></article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>839</fpage><lpage>843</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14985762</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02289</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic Flux Balancing: Basic concepts, Scientific and Practical Use &#x02013; 13 Years Later</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2008</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18536691</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nbt1401</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Vo</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An expanded genome-scale model of <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>K-12 (<italic>i</italic>JR904 GSM/GPR)</article-title><source>Genome Biology</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>R54.51</fpage><lpage>R54.52</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12952533</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/gb-2003-4-9-r54</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Varma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stoichiometric flux balance models quantitatively predict growth and metabolic by-product secretion in wild-type Escherichia coli W3110</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1994</year><volume>60</volume><fpage>3724</fpage><lpage>3731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7986045</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kanehisa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goto</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Aoki-Kinoshita</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Itoh</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kawashima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Katayama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Araki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hirakawa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>From genomics to chemical genomics: new developments in KEGG</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>D354</fpage><lpage>357</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16381885</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkj102</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Romero</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Karp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>PseudoCyc, A Pathway-Genome Database for Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Journal of Molecular Microbiology and Biotechnology</source><year>2003</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>239</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12867747</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000071075</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Choi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Munch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leupold</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Siegel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Thielen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Benkert</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kucklick</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schobert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthelmes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>SYSTOMONAS &#x02013; an integrated database for systems biology analysis of Pseudomonas</article-title><source>Nucl Acids Res</source><year>2007</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>D533</fpage><lpage>537</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17202169</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkl823</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Revelles</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittich</surname><given-names>R-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of the Initial Steps in D-Lysine Catabolism in Pseudomonas putida</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2007</year><volume>189</volume><fpage>2787</fpage><lpage>2792</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17259313</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01538-06</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huijberts</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>de Rijk</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Waard</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>13C nuclear magnetic resonance studies of Pseudomonas putida fatty acid metabolic routes involved in poly(3-hydroxyalkanoate) synthesis</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1994</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>1661</fpage><lpage>1666</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8132461</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hazer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinb&#x000fc;chel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Increased diversification of polyhydroxyalkanoates by modification reactions for industrial and medical applications</article-title><source>Appl Microbiol Biotechnol</source><year>2007</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>12</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17146652</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00253-006-0732-8</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Madison</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic Engineering of Poly(3-Hydroxyalkanoates): From DNA to Plastic</article-title><source>Microbiol Mol Biol Rev</source><year>1999</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>53</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066830</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oberhardt</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Puchalka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fryer</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name><name><surname>Martins dos Santos</surname><given-names>VAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Papin</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-Scale Metabolic Network Analysis of the Opportunistic Pathogen Pseudomonas aeruginosa PAO1</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2008</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>2790</fpage><lpage>2803</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18192387</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.01583-07</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B65"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janssen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldovsky</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kunin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Darzentas</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ouzounis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome coverage, literally speaking. The challenge of annotating 200 genomes with 4 million publications</article-title><source>EMBO Rep</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>397</fpage><lpage>399</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15864286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.embor.7400412</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B66"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Delhaize</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Function and mechanism Of Organic anion exudation from plant roots</article-title><source>Annual Review of Plant Physiology and Plant Molecular Biology</source><year>2001</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>560</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.arplant.52.1.527</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B67"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Espinosa-Urgel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a Pseudomonas putida Aminotransferase Involved in Lysine Catabolism Is Induced in the Rhizosphere</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2001</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>5219</fpage><lpage>5224</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11679348</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.67.11.5219-5224.2001</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B68"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stanier</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name><name><surname>Palleroni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Doudoroff</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The aerobic pseudomonads: a taxonomic study</article-title><source>J Gen Microbiol</source><year>1966</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>159</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5963505</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B69"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Galvao</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lorenzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Canovas</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Uncoupling of choline-O-sulphate utilization from osmoprotection in Pseudomonas putida</article-title><source>Molecular Microbiology</source><year>2006</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>1643</fpage><lpage>1654</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17116241</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2958.2006.05488.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B70"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vicente</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Canovas</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Glucolysis in Pseudomonas putida: Physiological Role of Alternative Routes from the Analysis of Defective Mutants</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1973</year><volume>116</volume><fpage>908</fpage><lpage>914</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4745434</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B71"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reed</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Famili</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Thiele</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards multidimensional genome annotation</article-title><source>Nat Rev Genet</source><year>2006</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16418748</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrg1769</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B72"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Worsey</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of toluene and xylenes by Pseudomonas (putida (arvilla) mt-2: evidence for a new function of the TOL plasmid</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1975</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>13</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1176436</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B73"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Assinder</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>PA</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The TOL plasmids: determinants of the catabolism of toluene and the xylenes</article-title><source>Adv Microb Physiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>31</volume><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2264522</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B74"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rekik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wubbolts</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Leppik</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterization of five genes in the upper-pathway operon of TOL plasmid pWW0 from Pseudomonas putida and identification of the gene products</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1989</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>5048</fpage><lpage>5055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2549010</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B75"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harayama</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rekik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The meta cleavage operon of TOL degradative plasmid pWW0 comprises 13 genes</article-title><source>Mol Gen Genet</source><year>1990</year><volume>221</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2183008</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00280375</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B76"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional control of the pseudomonas tol plasmid catabolic operons is achieved through an interplay of host factors and plasmid-encoded regulators</article-title><source>Annual Review of Microbiology</source><year>1997</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9343354</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.micro.51.1.341</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B77"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramakrishna</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>McCulloch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Flux-balance analysis of mitochondrial energy metabolism: consequences of systemic stoichiometric constraints</article-title><source>American journal of physiology</source><year>2001</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>R695</fpage><lpage>704</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171647</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B78"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Zamboni</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High-throughput metabolic flux analysis based on gas chromatography-mass spectrometry derived 13C constraints</article-title><source>Anal Biochem</source><year>2004</year><volume>325</volume><fpage>308</fpage><lpage>316</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14751266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ab.2003.10.036</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B79"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alagappan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of temperature and dissolved oxygen on the growth kinetics of Pseudomonas putida F1 growing on benzene and toluen</article-title><source>Chemosphere</source><year>2004</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1255</fpage><lpage>1265</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14664855</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.chemosphere.2003.09.013</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B80"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denef</surname><given-names>VJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klappenbach</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Patrauchan</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Florizone</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>JLM</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsoi</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Verstraete</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Eltis</surname><given-names>LD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic and Genomic Insights into the Role of Benzoate-Catabolic Pathway Redundancy in Burkholderia xenovorans LB400</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>585</fpage><lpage>595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16391095</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.72.1.585-595.2006</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B81"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fridovich</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superoxide radicals, superoxide dismutases and the aerobic lifestyle</article-title><source>Photochem Photobiol</source><year>1978</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>733</fpage><lpage>741</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">216032</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1751-1097.1978.tb07009.x</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B82"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Alwood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Thaipisuttikul</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Spencer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Haugen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Will</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaul</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Raymond</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Levy</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title>Comprehensive transposon mutant library of Pseudomonas aeruginosa</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2003</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>14339</fpage><lpage>14344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.2036282100</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B83"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liberati</surname><given-names>NT</given-names></name><name><surname>Urbach</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyata</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Drenkard</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Villanueva</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ausubel</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An ordered, nonredundant library of Pseudomonas aeruginosa strain PA14 transposon insertion mutants</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2006</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>2833</fpage><lpage>2838</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0511100103</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B84"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>de Roo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connor</surname><given-names>KE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of Polyhydroxyalkanoate from Styrene and Phenylacetic Acid by Pseudomonas putida CA-3</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>2046</fpage><lpage>2052</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15812037</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.4.2046-2052.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B85"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Timm</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbuchel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Formation of polyesters consisting of medium-chain-length 3-hydroxyalkanoic acids from gluconate by Pseudomonas aeruginosa and other fluorescent pseudomonads</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>3360</fpage><lpage>3367</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2125185</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B86"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgard</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pharkya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Maranas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optknock: a bilevel programming framework for identifying gene knockout strategies for microbial strain optimization</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2003</year><volume>84</volume><fpage>647</fpage><lpage>657</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14595777</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/bit.10803</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B87"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pharkya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgard</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maranas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>OptStrain: a computational framework for redesign of microbial production systems</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>2367</fpage><lpage>2376</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15520298</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.2872004</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B88"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hua</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Joyce</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolic analysis of adaptive evolution for in silico designed lactate-producing strains</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2006</year><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16807925</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B89"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>TY</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Systems biotechnology for strain improvement</article-title><source>Trends Biotechnol</source><year>2005</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>349</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15923052</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tibtech.2005.05.003</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B90"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abril</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Michan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Timmis</surname><given-names>KN</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulator and enzyme specificities of the TOL plasmid-encoded upper pathway for degradation of aromatic hydrocarbons and expansion of the substrate range of the pathway</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>1989</year><volume>171</volume><fpage>6782</fpage><lpage>6790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2687253</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B91"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fuhrer</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sauer</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Experimental Identification and Quantification of Glucose Metabolism in Seven Bacterial Species</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2005</year><volume>187</volume><fpage>1581</fpage><lpage>1590</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15716428</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JB.187.5.1581-1590.2005</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B92"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Feist</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mo</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannum</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrgard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox</article-title><source>Nat Protocols</source><year>2007</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>727</fpage><lpage>738</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nprot.2007.99</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B93"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neidhardt</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><name><surname>Ingraham</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaechter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Physiology of the bacterial cell: a molecular approach</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Sunderland, Mass.: Sinauer Associates</publisher-name></citation></ref><ref id="B94"><citation citation-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinkart</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name></person-group><source>Lipids of pseudomonas</source><publisher-name>Pseudomonas. Plenum Press</publisher-name><fpage>111</fpage><lpage>138</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B95"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>In silico predictions of Escherichia coli metabolic capabilities are consistent with experimental data</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/84379</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B96"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schilling</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Letscher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combining pathway analysis with flux balance analysis for the comprehensive study of metabolic systems</article-title><source>Biotechnol Bioeng</source><year>2000</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>286</fpage><lpage>306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11291038</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0290(2000)71:4&#x0003c;286::AID-BIT1018&#x0003e;3.0.CO;2-R</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B97"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Ibarra</surname><given-names>RU</given-names></name><name><surname>Palsson</surname><given-names>BO</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>In silico </italic>predictions of <italic>Escherichia coli </italic>metabolic capabilities are consistent with experimental data</article-title><source>Nat Biotechnol</source><year>2001</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11175725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/84379</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B98"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnaud</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Berlyn</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Blattner</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhuri</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name><name><surname>Glasner</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Horiuchi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Keseler</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kosuge</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal></etal></person-group><article-title><italic>Escherichia coli </italic>K-12: a cooperatively developed annotation snapshot-2005</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>2006</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>9</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16397293</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/nar/gkj405</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B99"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nogales</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Canales</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jimenez-Barbero</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Molecular Characterization of the Gallate Dioxygenase from Pseudomonas putida KT2440: The prototype of a new subgroup of extradiol dioxygenases</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>35382</fpage><lpage>35390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16030014</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M502585200</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B100"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodwell</surname><given-names>VW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Metabolism of Basic Amino Acids in Pseudomonas putida. Transport of lysine, ornithine, and arginine</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>1972</year><volume>247</volume><fpage>2283</fpage><lpage>2288</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5019949</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B101"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vilchez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Molina</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proline Catabolism by Pseudomonas putida: Cloning, Characterization, and Expression of the put Genes in the Presence of Root Exudates</article-title><source>J Bacteriol</source><year>2000</year><volume>182</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>99</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10613867</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B102"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haywood</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ewing</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawes</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Accumulation of a Polyhydroxyalkanoate Containing Primarily 3-Hydroxydecanoate from Simple Carbohydrate Substrates by Pseudomonas sp. Strain NCIMB 40135</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1990</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>3354</fpage><lpage>3359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16348341</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B103"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huisman</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>de Leeuw</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Eggink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Witholt</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synthesis of poly-3-hydroxyalkanoates is a common feature of fluorescent pseudomonads</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1989</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>1949</fpage><lpage>1954</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2506811</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>


